<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King at White-Hal, Septem. the 26th, 1675 by John Standish ...</title>
            <author>Standish, John, d. 1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61265</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5215</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13595</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13586999</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13586999</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100574</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61265)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100574)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 851:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King at White-Hal, Septem. the 26th, 1675 by John Standish ...</title>
                  <author>Standish, John, d. 1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>34, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published by His Majesties command."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 2nd, V, 20 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100574:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100574:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the KING AT WHITE-HAL, <hi>Septem.</hi> the 26<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1675.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Standiſh</hi> B.D. And one of His Majeſties Chaplains in Ordinary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by His Majeſties Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Brome,</hi> at the Gun in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1676.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:100574:2"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:100574:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 COR.</hi> Chap. <hi>5.</hi> ver. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Now then we are <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> for CHRIST, as though GOD did beſeech you by us, We pray you in CHRIST's ſtead, be ye reconciled to GOD.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He matter of the Context which St. <hi>Paul</hi> infers theſe words up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is of ſuch Tranſcendent Nature and Momentous Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that it may well beſpeak your attention with that Angel's awakening Preface on the like ſubject: <hi>Fear not, for behold, I bring you good tidings of great joy, which ſhall be to all people!</hi> 'Tis ſuch a ſtrange and raviſhing piece of News, as <hi>Corinth, the Eye</hi> of all <hi>Greece,</hi> could <hi>not ſee,</hi> till our Apoſtle made the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery: As the itching <hi>Ears</hi> at <hi>Athens</hi> had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>heard</hi> before He told it them too, from the <hi>UNKNOWN GOD;</hi> nor could it enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>heart</hi> of Jew or Gentile, Man or Angel, <hi>to conceive,</hi> till the Eternal <hi>WORD</hi> came down from Heaven on purpoſe to reveal it. 'Tis
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100574:3"/>that ſtupendous <hi>Myſtery hid from Ages;</hi> that moſt Magnificent, and moſt Kingly work of God (as <hi>Clemens</hi> calls it) the Myſtery of Man's <hi>Redemption;</hi> to wit, <hi>That God was in Chriſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling the World to himſelf, not imputing their treſpaſſes, making him to be ſin for us, that knew no ſin, that we might be made the Righteouſneſs of God in him,</hi> Rejoyce then, and <hi>be of good chear, O ſons of men,</hi> for <hi>your ſins are forgiven,</hi> Divine Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is ſatisfied, the Debt paid, the Bond can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell'd, the Priſon doors ſet ope, and an Act of General Pardon paſs'd in the Court of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and ſeal'd on Earth with the Blood of <hi>GOD</hi> Himſelf, to make it more <hi>unchangeable</hi> than any Decree of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians.</hi> The caſe is ſo well alter'd with the Bankrupt, Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>law'd Seed of <hi>Adam,</hi> that nothing hinders now; but all men may be ſaved and made for ever, if they ſtand not in their own light: All de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees amongſt them, from the Judge of <hi>Areo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagus,</hi> to the Jailor at <hi>Philippi;</hi> from the <hi>Lord Treaſurer</hi> of <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> to the Beggar at the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-gate; from the <hi>Elect Lady,</hi> to the Widow <hi>Dorcas;</hi> from the Houſhold of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> to that of <hi>Stephanas;</hi> from the <hi>KING</hi> himſelf that ſits upon the <hi>Throne,</hi> to him that grindeth at
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100574:3"/>the <hi>Mill,</hi> all have an undoubted Right and Title to God the <hi>Father's</hi> Mercy, if they will but <hi>kiſs</hi> and <hi>reverence</hi> the <hi>Son;</hi> there's nothing wanting but their own conſent to make them all <hi>Heirs of God, Joint-heirs with Chriſt</hi> to ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Glory. Conſent? Why, will there be any demur upon that? 'Tis not to part with, but take poſſeſſion of an Inheritance purchas'd for them: Not to <hi>merit</hi> or <hi>buy,</hi> but only to accept and wear an Immortal <hi>Crown.</hi> All's a caſe; Man is a wilful, wiſe, and ſtately Creature, that muſt be woed and courted to his own Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity: And our gracious <hi>LORD</hi> (bleſſed be his name) hath made due Proviſion for that alſo; for when he <hi>aſcended up on high to his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer glory,</hi> he left not us to the wide World, nor <hi>Himſelf</hi> without a <hi>witneſs in doing us good:</hi> For he founded a certain Order of men on purpoſe to be his <hi>Delegates</hi> and <hi>Vicars,</hi> to <hi>preach the Goſpel of Peace every where, and Remiſsion of ſins in his name,</hi> ſaying, as my <hi>Father ſent me, ſo ſend I you, and lo I am with you, and your</hi> Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, <hi>to the Worlds end:</hi> To them he committed his Word of <hi>Reconciliation,</hi> obliging them by all that is Sacred, to leave no ſtone unturn'd, but uſe all laudable means to perſwade and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100574:4"/>men (as in his own perſon) to come in upon Proclamation, that they may have life. <hi>Now then We are Ambaſſadors,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In the words I ſhall conſider: 1. The Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the Evangelical Miniſtry; which is, 1. General, <hi>Ambaſſadors;</hi> and then more ſpecial and diſtinguiſhing, Ambaſſadors for <hi>CHRIST.</hi> 2. The ſubject <hi>matter,</hi> ſum and purport of their <hi>Ambaſſy,</hi> be ye <hi>reconciled to God.</hi> 3. Their <hi>manner of Addreſs,</hi> in delivering this <hi>Ambaſſy,</hi> as <hi>though God did beſeech you by us,</hi> we <hi>pray you in Chriſt's ſtead.</hi> I begin with the firſt; and, 1. With their <hi>general Character,</hi> We are <hi>Ambaſſadors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An <hi>Ambaſſador</hi> is properly one that repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents his <hi>KING</hi> in a <hi>Foreign</hi> Country, as a Deputy or Lieutenant doth in his <hi>own Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> whoſe buſineſs is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as the old Greeks call it) to manage his Maſters Affairs, Power and Polity <hi>abroad;</hi> to treat with other great <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Emperors</hi> upon the moſt weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty matters: Whereby (I ſuppoſe) he is diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd from <hi>Nuncio's, Agents,</hi> and other modern names of ſuch as are either ſent to <hi>petty Princes,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:100574:4"/>like thoſe of <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Germany;</hi> or if to <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigns,</hi> upon <hi>State-Ceremony,</hi> or Meſſages of <hi>leſſer</hi> moment.</p>
            <p>By this <hi>high</hi> Metaphor, the Apoſtle here calls the <hi>Evangelical Miniſtry;</hi> and that (as I conceive) for ſome or other of the enſuing Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. An <hi>Ambaſſador</hi> is ſuppos'd to be a man of <hi>Integrity, faithful</hi> to his Inſtructions, and <hi>true</hi> to his important Truſt. No Gifts or Penſions can tempt his impregnable Fidelity to a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render: He's not to be practis'd upon, or won to baſe Compliances with a <hi>Foreign Crown;</hi> as knowing, that if he be taken tardy, or make excurſions beyond his Line, if by his <hi>fraud</hi> or <hi>falſeneſs,</hi> he loſe the leaſt <hi>hair</hi> of his Maſters honour, it may chance to coſt him his own <hi>head.</hi> Much more is it requir'd of them in the Text, as <hi>Stewards</hi> of the <hi>Myſteries of God,</hi> that they be found faithful unto the death. The <hi>falſe</hi> Prophet ſaid, but <hi>true</hi> in that, though <hi>Balac</hi> would <hi>give me the houſe full of Gold and Silver, I cannot go beyond the Commandment of the Lord.</hi> They dare not ſay, <hi>Peace, peace, when there is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100574:5"/>no peace;</hi> nor flatter any man living in his ſins, to gain <hi>half a Kingdom.</hi> When they addreſs to one of the <hi>Potentates</hi> (ſays <hi>Epictetus</hi>) they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member there is <hi>Another above,</hi> that ſees and hears all that paſſes; and of the two, they are moſt obliged to pleaſe or fear <hi>Him.</hi> His ſurly Yeomen of the Guard could not force the <hi>Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonian Legates</hi> to fall down and worſhip the <hi>mighty Perſian Monarch,</hi> becauſe againſt the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Law of <hi>Lycurgus:</hi> From whence <hi>Origen</hi> infers, much leſs ſhould <hi>Men</hi> or <hi>Devils</hi> affright them that are engag'd in this more Divine <hi>Ambaſſy,</hi> to give away their Maſters honour to the King of <hi>Perſin, Greece,</hi> or <hi>any other,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contrary to the whole Tenour of his Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Goſpel. Wherefore let all ſuch as <hi>Judas</hi>-like, betray their Maſter for a few ſhekels of Silver; or teach the <hi>Traditions</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines</hi> of <hi>Devils,</hi> for the Word of <hi>God,</hi> be (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) <hi>Anathema Maranatha;</hi> that is, ſtand condemned till their Lord come.</p>
            <p n="2">2. An <hi>Ambaſſador</hi> is preſum'd to be one of more than common <hi>Prudence, Sagacity</hi> and <hi>Judgment,</hi> that underſtands his Errand through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſuch <hi>Imperial Laws</hi> as concern the Pleas
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100574:5"/>of his Maſters Crown. <hi>Plutarch</hi> is too light and jocular, when he's for ſending them that moſt <hi>deſire,</hi> and leaſt <hi>deſerve</hi> it, that ſo they may be expos'd and <hi>laugh'd</hi> at: For it is no <hi>laughing</hi> matter ſure, when <hi>Crowns</hi> and <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms</hi> lie at ſtake: They had more need be men of good Wiſdom and Brains, that can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern and nick the different Humour and Guiſe of divers Countries, can ſoar aloft, and treat the <hi>Italian</hi> in a Circuit of Pompous words (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſtoop to the <hi>Point;</hi>) and be as blunt with the <hi>Switzers,</hi> that <hi>hate</hi> all Language: That underſtand the great Art of <hi>Timing things well;</hi> there being (ſays <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>a proper ſeaſon for every purpoſe under Heaven.</hi> I am ſure, our Lord charges his Ambaſſadors (ſaving their Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence) to be wiſe as <hi>Serpents,</hi> as being to deal with that Politick <hi>Old</hi> Serpent, and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the depths of <hi>Satan.</hi> On this account St. <hi>Paul</hi> became <hi>all things to all men,</hi> that <hi>he might by all means ſave ſome.</hi> For one <hi>Remedy</hi> will not ſerve for every <hi>Diſeaſe;</hi> nor are all <hi>Truths</hi> proper to be ſpoken at all times. Our Saviour did not challenge the Jews for <hi>Idolatry</hi> or <hi>Uſury,</hi> but for <hi>ſpiritual Pride, Hypocriſie</hi> and <hi>Traditions</hi> (where the ſhooe pincht:) But then his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100574:6"/>
               <hi>turning</hi> to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> fell foul upon <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition</hi> and <hi>Idolatry</hi> (their common Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers) the firſt thing they did; to inform their Succeſſors, that they ſhould not ſpend their breath in declaiming againſt ſins quite out of <hi>faſhion,</hi> or confuting old <hi>obſolete</hi> Hereſies (which were much like killing a man that was dead before;) or treating <hi>Chriſtian Aſſemblies</hi> with the ſame Diſcourſe that might better ſerve to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the <hi>Great Turk.</hi> They ſhould not handle profeſſed <hi>Chriſtians</hi> (though never ſo <hi>Carnal</hi>) as <hi>Origen, Juſtin Martyr</hi> or <hi>Tertullian</hi> did <hi>rank Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then;</hi> nor lay out all their pains and oyl about the firſt <hi>Elements,</hi> though it be to demonſtrate <hi>our Religion</hi> to be the <hi>beſt</hi> of all others, and moſt <hi>perfective</hi> of <hi>Humane Nature:</hi> For <hi>Principles</hi> are not to be made <hi>cheap,</hi> and every day brought upon the <hi>Stage,</hi> ſpecially where they were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver denied. What though one man commit <hi>Murther,</hi> another <hi>Adultery,</hi> a third <hi>Treaſon,</hi> a fourth <hi>Blaſphemy;</hi> muſt I go prove in all haſte, and upon every turn, that there is a <hi>GOD?</hi> They <hi>all</hi> know that as well as I, unleſs they will in their Huffs deny their <hi>own Being,</hi> and belye their own <hi>Conſciences:</hi> by Arguments too far fetch'd, or proving <hi>too much,</hi> we prove <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:100574:6"/>at all, or that which no man queſtions. Prudence ſhould rather teach us, with due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to <hi>time, place</hi> and <hi>perſons,</hi> to bend our ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſtrength and main counſels againſt the <hi>preſent</hi> and moſt <hi>predominant</hi> Errours, whether in <hi>Faith</hi> or <hi>Morals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. An <hi>Ambaſſador</hi> ſhould have compentent <hi>Eloquence,</hi> a <hi>Tongue well hung</hi> (we ſay) for that his proper buſineſs is to <hi>ſpeak,</hi> and he is ſaid to have his <hi>Audience</hi> as an <hi>Orator.</hi> He is to effect that which <hi>equity</hi> perſwades, or neceſſity requires by force of <hi>Argument,</hi> to prevent the force of <hi>Arms,</hi> and that is not to be done by a mere noiſe and flood of words, without one drop of ſenſe; but he muſt be able to ſpeak powerfully, to move, charm, lead mens hearts in triumph, and conquer minds with the pleaſing Arms of Eloquence. <hi>Antipater</hi> therefore deſir'd the <hi>Athenians</hi> to ſend their <hi>Orator</hi> no more to <hi>Him,</hi> becauſe by his prodigious Art of ſpeaking (were the cauſe <hi>right</hi> or <hi>wrong</hi>) he baffled and topp'd all offers made againſt him. Now that St. <hi>Paul</hi> alludes here prfeſſedly to this property, I appeal to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>ſtile</hi> of the Text: Only there is this difference
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100574:7"/>between <hi>CHRISTS</hi> Ambaſſadors and all <hi>others,</hi> that <hi>they</hi> rely not upon their own ſtrength of parts and <hi>Oratory,</hi> nor take up with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Artifices and <hi>enticing words of mans wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> but their chief <hi>Rhetorick</hi> and height of <hi>Eloquence</hi> lies in the <hi>Demonſtration of the Spirit, Power</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, An <hi>Ambaſſador</hi> yet lacks <hi>one thing</hi> more before he goes; that is, a <hi>Commiſsion,</hi> to make his Acts <hi>Authentick,</hi> which were other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>null</hi> and <hi>void,</hi> and himſelf a great <hi>Cheat. Demoſthenes</hi> hath left a laſting Brand of Infamy upon <hi>Aeſchines,</hi> for going <hi>Ambaſſador</hi> to <hi>Philip</hi> on his own head: But whether we ſhould take the <hi>Orator</hi> for a faithful <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> in the caſe, may be perhaps a <hi>queſtion.</hi> No <hi>queſtion</hi> ſuch an Act were <hi>crimen laetae Majeſtatis</hi> in all <hi>Empires;</hi> nay <hi>Treaſon</hi> in a very high degree, it being a greater affront to <hi>Sovereignty,</hi> to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit a King's <hi>Perſon,</hi> than either his Royal <hi>Coyn, Hand</hi> or <hi>Seal.</hi> Thus St. <hi>Paul</hi> demands per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptorily, How ſhall they <hi>preach,</hi> except they be <hi>ſent?</hi> that is, they are <hi>falſe Apoſtles, Traytors</hi> to God's everlaſting <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Dignity,</hi> that do preſume it. Be a man never ſo gifted
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100574:7"/>and able, never ſuch a <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Thunder,</hi> never ſo <hi>Eloquent</hi> and <hi>Mighty</hi> in <hi>the Scriptures;</hi> yet without due Authority, he hath no <hi>part</hi> or <hi>lot in this matter: For no man taketh this honour to himſelf, but he that is called of God, as was Aaron, Heb.</hi> 5. Now as the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were in quality of <hi>Ambaſſadors extraordinary, commiſsioned</hi> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately by <hi>CHRIST</hi> himſelf, and endued with mighty gifts of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> neceſſary for the firſt planting of the <hi>Chriſtian Faith:</hi> So their lawful Succeſſors are <hi>Leigers,</hi> and <hi>in ordinary called alſo of God;</hi> but by the Mediation of thoſe <hi>Men,</hi> on whom the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> derived their <hi>Miſsion</hi> and <hi>Unction</hi> they received from <hi>CHRIST.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we ſee in what ſenſe they are <hi>Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors,</hi> and pardon me if I hence <hi>infer,</hi> that they ought to be received as <hi>ſuch,</hi> and <hi>account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed worthy</hi> of ſingle <hi>honour</hi> and reſpect (at leaſt) for their very <hi>Work</hi> and <hi>Office</hi> ſake.</p>
            <p>To aſſert the Dignity of this <hi>Holy Calling</hi> amongſt <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> was once indeed <hi>ſuperfluous,</hi> when men were ready to adore and <hi>ſacrifice</hi> to them as <hi>Gods,</hi> and <hi>pluck out their own eyes for them:</hi> But is perhaps as <hi>neceſſary</hi> now, when the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100574:8"/>World is run into the other <hi>extreme,</hi> and ſo far from <hi>communicating to them all good things;</hi> (<hi>Gal.</hi> 6.) that they will hardly give them <hi>one good word:</hi> When the <hi>Apoſtate</hi> Emperours Scoff is ſo often laid in their diſh, That <hi>CHRIST</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> deſpiſed the Wealth and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of this World: Though the arguing is moſt inconſequent, from their times of <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution,</hi> to ours of <hi>Peace;</hi> from <hi>Heathen</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires, to <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Monarchies. Beſides, if they take the <hi>Context</hi> along with them, they will find, that in thoſe days <hi>Lay-Chriſtians</hi> had as little repute or <hi>wealth</hi> as the <hi>Clergy; all they had</hi> (though ne're ſo much) was freely <hi>laid down</hi> at thoſe poor <hi>Apoſtles feet,</hi> for the publick ſervice of the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for thoſe little mighty <hi>Wits,</hi> and goodly Maſters of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that are ever whetting their <hi>Tongues</hi> and <hi>Pens</hi> to expoſe them to <hi>contempt;</hi> alas, they utterly miſs their aim; for it is the credit of our <hi>Religion</hi> and its <hi>Miniſters,</hi> that <hi>Nero</hi> ſpake, <hi>Celſus</hi> wrote, and <hi>Julian</hi> acted againſt them. They are not moved at <hi>Celſus</hi> his prodigious <hi>Calumny,</hi> that they <hi>conjured</hi> and dealt with <hi>familiar Spirits;</hi> when (God knows) they
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100574:8"/>only caſt them out in the Name of <hi>JESUS.</hi> They rejoyce to ſuffer <hi>ſhame,</hi> and be Nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>Fops, Formaliſts,</hi> and <hi>Thinking-Fools,</hi> by men of the ſame ſpirit with them that ſaid the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> himſelf had a <hi>Devil.</hi> But yet theſe <hi>Hero's</hi> might remember in their <hi>cold blood,</hi> and <hi>ſober</hi> intervals (if they have any) that as it is againſt the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nations</hi> to caſt dirt upon, and offer indignities to an <hi>Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor,</hi> ſo the affront aims chiefly at his <hi>Prince;</hi> and ſuch as <hi>deſpiſe them, deſpiſe him that ſent them,</hi> who will in due time redeem his own Honour, and pay <hi>them</hi> that they have <hi>deſerved:</hi> Mean while we'll be <hi>reveng'd</hi> of them too, but only in our <hi>Churches Prayer</hi> (and God ſpeed it well!) that it may <hi>pleaſe him to forgive our Enemies, Perſecutors</hi> and <hi>Slanderers,</hi> and <hi>to turn their hearts.</hi> But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. You need not fear the <hi>Sons of</hi> Levi <hi>ſhould take</hi> too <hi>much upon them</hi> in this <hi>high Title,</hi> if you conſider their more <hi>ſpecial Character,</hi> as they are Ambaſſadors for <hi>CHRIST.</hi> A <hi>King</hi> indeed, but one whoſe <hi>Kingdom</hi> was not of <hi>this World:</hi> Who never uſed more <hi>ſecular</hi> Pomp in all his life, but once <hi>riding into</hi> Jeruſalem
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100574:9"/>
               <hi>upon an Aſſes Colt:</hi> A <hi>King</hi> indeed, but his Courtiers poor <hi>Fiſhermen</hi> and <hi>Publicans;</hi> his Scepter a <hi>Reed,</hi> his Crown made of <hi>Thorns,</hi> and his Throne an ignominious <hi>Croſs:</hi> And his <hi>Diſciples are not greater than their Lord,</hi> they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not to diſpoſe of <hi>Crowns</hi> and <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> (let Him at <hi>Rome</hi> anſwer for that, who ſays, we know by what Right and Precedent, <hi>All theſe will I give thee:</hi>) They claim no <hi>Secular</hi> Honours or Priviledges, but what they owe to the pious Bounty of <hi>Chriſtian Princes,</hi> who are graciouſly pleas'd to treat them as <hi>Prophets;</hi> and ſhall therefore receive a <hi>Prophets</hi> reward: <hi>Their power</hi> (ſays a Learned man) is <hi>armed only with a ſpiritual Sword (the wounds whereof are little felt or dreaded in this World) ſupported moſtly with a mean temporal Fortune; yet it has ſtood hitherto againſt all Oppoſition, and ſhall ſtand for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whether they meet with Friends or Foes, Love or Hatred, Frowns or Favours <hi>here,</hi> they are ſure of a Reward moſt glorious here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, if they can but give their <hi>Maſter</hi> (who is ſince declared <hi>King of kings</hi>) a good account of their great <hi>Errand</hi> and <hi>Buſineſs</hi> here on Earth. Which leads me to the ſecond thing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100574:9"/>conſiderable, The <hi>ſubject matter, ſum</hi> and <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</hi> of their <hi>Ambaſſy,</hi> in thoſe words, <hi>Be ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled unto God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reconciliation</hi> imports a returning into <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour</hi> and <hi>Friendſhip,</hi> after a former <hi>Enmity</hi> or <hi>Falling-out</hi> between Parties. Now though <hi>man</hi> be the ſole Party <hi>offending,</hi> that made the breach by <hi>ſin,</hi> his own <hi>voluntary</hi> act; yet <hi>God</hi> hath been graciouſly <hi>reconciled</hi> to Him ever ſince the hour of <hi>CHRISTS</hi> death, which he accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as a <hi>full</hi> and <hi>perfect ſatisfaction for the ſins of the whole World:</hi> All the difficulty is (which ſo many <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> are daily ſent about) to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with <hi>man</hi> to be reconciled to <hi>God. Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled?</hi> Surely that muſt be an <hi>hard ſaying,</hi> clogg'd with ſome impoſſible Condition, that makes men ſtart ſo at, fly from, and not endure to hear on't. Yes, it is ſo; for it requires them to do—What ſhall I ſay? to do juſt <hi>nothing,</hi> in compariſon; rather to be <hi>paſsive</hi> (as the Verb <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here is) and not hinder <hi>God</hi> from making them <hi>happy.</hi> Yes; it requires them to renounce their own Merits (and that's a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty piece of <hi>Self-denial</hi> for wretched ſinners that never had <hi>any</hi>) and then cry <hi>Peccavi,</hi> before
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100574:10"/>they can obtain <hi>Mercy:</hi> It lays that <hi>grievous</hi> bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then upon them, to be <hi>Friends</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſuffer <hi>God</hi> to be ſo far <hi>Lord</hi> of their <hi>Wills,</hi> as to advance them (like the great <hi>Abraham</hi>) to be his boſom <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Favourites.</hi> In a word, and not to mince the matter, there being no <hi>name under Heaven, whereby we can be ſaved, but</hi> the <hi>name of JESUS,</hi> it requires us all to believe ſtedfaſtly in, and depend wholly upon <hi>Him,</hi> both for <hi>pardon</hi> of our ſins, and <hi>power</hi> againſt them. 1. For <hi>Pardon,</hi> we muſt ſue <hi>that</hi> out in and through his <hi>Death;</hi> for without his <hi>precious, Bloodſhed, there is no Remiſsion of ſins;</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out our acceptance, none for <hi>us</hi> however. Though there be <hi>Balm in</hi> Gilead, and a <hi>Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an there,</hi> yet if men will not uſe them, no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if they <hi>periſh,</hi> and <hi>their blood be upon their own heads:</hi> They may think never ſo well of their own <hi>Works</hi> and <hi>Ways,</hi> but when all is done, they muſt take Sanctuary in that <hi>new and living Way, which he conſecrated for us through the veil,</hi> that is, <hi>his Fleſh,</hi> Hebr. 10. or they're un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done for ever. For as we are not of kin to <hi>CHRIST,</hi> but only by the <hi>Mother's</hi> ſide, as he is <hi>fleſh of our fleſh, and bone of our bone,</hi> and God the <hi>Father</hi> doth forgive no mans ſins,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100574:10"/>but for <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Merits, offer'd in <hi>our Nature</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Croſs:</hi> And ſo doth he convey <hi>this</hi> and all other Bleſſings to us, only through his <hi>Son</hi> as our <hi>Mediator;</hi> that is, through his <hi>Humanity,</hi> as the only <hi>Band</hi> by which we are <hi>united</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled</hi> to the <hi>Divine Nature.</hi> Wherefore, 2. We muſt depend upon him alſo for <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> againſt <hi>ſin,</hi> by virtue of his <hi>Reſurrection</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> to purifie our <hi>Hearts</hi> and <hi>Conſciences,</hi> and keep that Tyrant <hi>Sin</hi> from <hi>reigning</hi> (at leaſt) <hi>in our</hi> mortal Bodies. Never did the moſt <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Prince</hi> pardon <hi>Rebels,</hi> but upon that <hi>one</hi> Condition, That they would turn <hi>Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects:</hi> Therefore (ſays St. <hi>Paul</hi>) if any man be in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he is a <hi>new Creature;</hi> he has a <hi>new</hi> heart, <hi>new</hi> deſires, <hi>new</hi> principles, <hi>new</hi> life, all things <hi>new:</hi> He's not the <hi>ſame</hi> man, he's quite chang'd, like the <hi>Prodigal Son, come to himſelf,</hi> to a ſenſe of his <hi>former</hi> follies, and <hi>preſent</hi> wants; or like the <hi>man among the Tombs,</hi> who when the <hi>Devils</hi> were gone out of him, ſate <hi>dutifully at Jeſus feet, clothed, and in his right mind.</hi> This is indeed the hardeſt <hi>Chapter</hi> in all our <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>Reconciliation;</hi> but yet he that <hi>runs</hi> may <hi>read</hi> it, if (with holy <hi>David</hi>) he takes the right <hi>courſe, Commit thy way unto the Lord, and put thy truſt in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100574:11"/>him, and he ſhall bring it to paſs:</hi> For is there any thing impoſſible with <hi>God.</hi> The <hi>heart</hi> of all men, even of <hi>Kings</hi> (ſays <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>is in the hand of the Lord, as Rivers of water, he turneth it whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſoever he pleaſeth.</hi> What though Nature of it ſelf be weak and impotent, ſo long as it is now <hi>endued with power from on high?</hi> Indeed our Saviour tells us plainly (to ſhew us our own inſufficiency) <hi>without Me ye can do nothing:</hi> But St. <hi>Paul</hi> as truly anſwers for himſelf, and us al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, <hi>I can do all things through CHRIST that ſtrengthens me.</hi> And when we read that ſuch <hi>Vertue went out</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (whilſt in the <hi>form of a Servant</hi>) that it cur'd the <hi>Woman</hi> of her <hi>Bloody Iſſue,</hi> upon but touching the <hi>Hem</hi> of his <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> why ſhould it ſeem incredible that his glorified Humane Nature (now he is <hi>Lord of all</hi>) ſhould diſtil his vertual Preſence and Life upon our Souls, to heal our infirmities? that he ſhould impart his own Graces to us, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive certain <hi>meaſures</hi> of the ſame <hi>holy Spirit</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, which himſelf <hi>as man,</hi> had <hi>without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure;</hi> becauſe in <hi>him the fulneſs of the Godhead dwelt bodily?</hi> Why ſhould it be thought ſtrange, that this holy Spirit that united <hi>GOD</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> in one Perſon, ſhould as <hi>really</hi> unite
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100574:11"/>us to our own Nature in <hi>CHRIST,</hi> the <hi>Body to the Head,</hi> the <hi>Branches to the Vine,</hi> and <hi>make him dwell in us,</hi> and <hi>us in him; him one with us, and us with him,</hi> as the Scripture ſpeaks. If any man think our <hi>Union</hi> with <hi>CRIST</hi> to be merely <hi>Political;</hi> that is, no more than you may conceive between <hi>King Bramble</hi> (in the Parable) and the reſt of the <hi>Trees</hi> his <hi>Subjects,</hi> he is in a very novel and groſs miſtake: To which I ſhall at preſent only oppoſe the words of two or three ſound Divines of our own Church; <hi>Though the Holy Ghoſt doth work Faith and other Graces in our Souls, yet he doth not by theſe unite our Souls or Spirits immediately to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but unto CHRISTS Humane Nature:</hi> So the profound Dr. <hi>Jackſon; CHRIST is as truly united to me, and I to him, as my arm is uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and knit to my ſhoulder:</hi> So the Judicious <hi>Hooker</hi> in plain Engliſh, <hi>By the influence of his preſent life, CHRIST undergoes, as it were, a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Incarnation, living and dwelling in our hearts by his Grace, and reigning powerfully in our ſouls by Faith:</hi> So the Learned <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> to add no more. So that upon the whole matter, the ſum of our <hi>Ambaſſy</hi> is this, That <hi>JESUS CHRIST</hi> is both the <hi>Author and finiſher of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100574:12"/>our Faith;</hi> that he hath ſolemnly promis'd to <hi>give his holy Spirit to them that ask him;</hi> that if men be not wanting to themſelves, but reſign their hearts to his Conduct, nay, if they don't forcibly <hi>reſiſt</hi> him, and quench the holy flames he kindles in their Souls, through his Servants Miniſtry, he will make them real partakers of the Grace of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> by working in them a firm Hope, fervent Love, pure Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, clean Heart, ſober Mind, chaſt Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, pious Soul, holy Life, and firſt and laſt, a true Faith in <hi>JESUS CHRIST;</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which it is <hi>impoſsible to pleaſe,</hi> or to be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if theſe things be ſo, I cannot but animadvert a while upon thoſe <hi>falſe Apoſtles,</hi> and <hi>deceitful Workers,</hi> who inſtead of building, are ever pecking at the Foundation of our Faith with their <hi>Axes</hi> and <hi>Hammers,</hi> in great <hi>Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> and leſſer <hi>Criticiſms,</hi> to change the <hi>old ſound word</hi> of <hi>Reconciliation,</hi> for new Ideas, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of their own, and other mens Brains: That would ſupplant <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion with <hi>Natural</hi> Theologie; and turn the <hi>Grace</hi> of God into a <hi>wanton</hi> Notion of <hi>Morality;</hi> that impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100574:12"/>deny both the <hi>Lord that bought them</hi> and his <hi>Holy Spirit, that ſhould ſeal them to the day of Redemption,</hi> making <hi>Reaſon, Reaſon, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> their only <hi>Trinity,</hi> and ſole Standard, whereby to meaſure both the Principles and Concluſions of <hi>Faith;</hi> that preach up <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Moral</hi> Religion, without the <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Faith in Chriſt;</hi> which is at beſt, beginning at the wrong end, and making Superſtructures without a Foundation: For the <hi>Jew</hi> cannot be ſaved by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> much leſs the <hi>Gentile</hi> by all the Works of the Law of <hi>Nature;</hi> which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs actuated by a lively <hi>Faith,</hi> are no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the <hi>cutting off a Dogs neck,</hi> or the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of a Fool.</hi> A Truth that <hi>Socrates</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf (in an ancient Dialogue aſcribed to <hi>Plato</hi>) makes no ſcruple to conſent unto, when he ſays ingenuouſly—that <hi>no man can be good and vertuous by Nature, Art, Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, Example, or any other manner of way, but only by Divine Inſpiration:</hi> So far do they out-ſtrip a very <hi>Heathen,</hi> that teach—<hi>a good Life will carry men to Heaven, though they be
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100574:13"/>Jews, Turks, Antichriſtians, or never ſuch damnable Hereticks in point of Faith.</hi> If any ſuch as theſe be <hi>crept in among</hi> us <hi>unawares,</hi> I am ſure there is as much need of a <hi>Teſt</hi> for <hi>them</hi> (how ſlily ſoever they carry it by amuſing the World with other fears) as for the rankeſt Errour in all the <hi>Pope's</hi> Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. And I beſeech you (Brethren in our <hi>LORD</hi>) beware of them: Ye ſhall <hi>know them by their Fruits,</hi> as <hi>He</hi> Himſelf fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels you: He does not mean the <hi>Fruits</hi> of their Lives (for they are the cloſeſt of all other <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> they <hi>go</hi> demurely in <hi>Sheeps clothing too:</hi>) But the <hi>Fruits</hi> and Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents of their Doctrine; which are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal enough (one would think) to make themſelves <hi>afraid,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> was of his own <hi>Rod</hi> turn'd into a <hi>Serpent:</hi> For they are ſuch as theſe—<hi>That there is no ſuch thing as ſupernatural Grace—That CHRIST dyed in vain—That ye are yet in your ſins—and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man muſt be his own Saviour, or he is damn'd for ever.</hi> From which—Good <hi>LORD</hi> deliver us! and <hi>GOD</hi> grant, that, by the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100574:13"/>Wiſdom and Vigilance of the <hi>Defender</hi> of our <hi>Faith,</hi> and his <hi>Prelates</hi> under <hi>Him,</hi> no ſuch Foreign Poyſon may be privily conveighed (through Preſs or Pulpit) into our <hi>Church:</hi> That thoſe black-mouth'd Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors bearing date from <hi>Irenopolis,</hi> may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſo <hi>timely</hi> and <hi>publick</hi> a check, as that we ſhall not need to fear their growing the only <hi>Divines</hi> in Vogue by the next Age: That we may never live to ſee our Youth trained up in the <hi>Cracovian Catechiſm;</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver live to hear our ſelves called by any other <hi>New Name,</hi> but that of <hi>GOD'S</hi> own giving: That as the Diſciples were <hi>firſt</hi> called at <hi>Antioch,</hi> ſo they may be <hi>laſt</hi> called <hi>CHRISTIANS</hi> here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I come to the third and laſt part of my Text, The <hi>manner</hi> of the true <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> Addreſs; in thoſe words—<hi>As though GOD did beſeech you by us, We pray you in CHRIST'S ſtead.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:100574:14"/>
            <p> Which is firſt modeſt and humble: <hi>We pray and beſeech.</hi> Let thoſe Haughty <hi>Poliſh Envoys</hi> ſwagger themſelves and others out of their <hi>Creed:</hi> Let the <hi>Diſciplinarian Agents</hi> Reprobate all the World, but their own private <hi>Elect:</hi> Let the <hi>Pope's</hi> Legates <hi>à La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere, Lord it</hi> over mens Eſtates and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; let <hi>Them will</hi> and <hi>require</hi> all upon pain of Damnation, to put their necks un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his feet, who in the Pride of his heart writes himſelf, <hi>Servus Servorum,</hi> that is (in the Vulgar Tranſlation) <hi>Lord of lords:</hi> As for us we have no ſuch Meſſage, we have not <hi>ſo learned Chriſt.</hi> We only pray you as <hi>men</hi> for whom <hi>CHRIST died, quit your ſelves like men,</hi> and fly to Mercy ſpeedily, leſt you fall into the hands of Juſtice, by letting your <hi>Sun go down upon the Wrath of God.</hi> You have all a merciful Saviour, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did, never will refuſe a ſincere Penitent (if you will take his own word for it) <hi>Him that cometh unto me,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>I will in no wiſe,</hi> by
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100574:14"/>no means <hi>caſt out.</hi> We beſeech you as <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> who have not only heard <hi>there is a Holy Ghoſt,</hi> but are baptized into the name of the Eternal <hi>TRINITY;</hi> have often <hi>taſted of the heavenly Gifts and Powers of the World to come.</hi> We beſeech you let the <hi>love of CHRIST conſtrain you,</hi> to improve the Talent put into your hand, and ſuffer his Holy Spirit to blow up thoſe ſparks of Grace ye have covered o're with aſhes in your hearts. O let not that Bleſſed <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter</hi> depart finally from you for the World, as he did from <hi>Saul;</hi> (for then an Evil Spirit will ſoon poſſeſs and vex, and ſend you to <hi>Endor:</hi>) But if ye have neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected his Grace, and fallen into ſin (as who can plead Not-guilty? Who can tell <hi>how oft he offendeth?</hi>) implore his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance <hi>heartily,</hi> wait his approach <hi>humbly,</hi> and attend his motions <hi>earneſtly,</hi> and he will raiſe you again to <hi>Newneſs of Life,</hi> he will bring you freſh Auxiliaries from your <hi>glorified Saviour,</hi> and in due time unite you
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100574:15"/>ſo firmly unto <hi>Him,</hi> that your ſins ſhall be chargeable only upon <hi>Him; His</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits put on your Accompt, and ſufficient <hi>Vertue ſhall go out of Him to cleanſe you from all Unrighteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And laſtly, be their <hi>Addreſs</hi> never ſo <hi>humble,</hi> it runs in a more then <hi>Humane</hi> ſtile; for, <hi>We pray you in CHRIST'S ſtead,</hi> and however you put us off till a a more <hi>convenient ſeaſon:</hi> Yet (as the voice from Heaven ſaid) <hi>hear HIM; HIM</hi> that once took the <hi>Curſe</hi> of God upon him for you, and is ever at his right hand in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceding for his <hi>Bleſsings</hi> on you: <hi>HIM,</hi> to whom <hi>all power is committed both in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth;</hi> who even as Son of <hi>Man,</hi> is now Lord of <hi>Angels, Lord of all.</hi> The Requeſts of <hi>Kings</hi> have been uſed to go for Commands with dutiful <hi>Subjects;</hi> And when the <hi>KING OF KINGS prays</hi> and begs but one thing of you, can ye poſſibly deny <hi>Him?</hi> Sure no <hi>Man</hi> can be ſo much a <hi>Monſter;</hi> no <hi>Gentleman</hi> ſo much a <hi>Jew.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100574:15"/>We pray you in Chriſt's ſtead:</hi> What ſhall I ſay more? Yes; not only the glorified Son of <hi>Man,</hi> but <hi>GOD</hi> himſelf doth <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you by us too.</hi> Wonder not that he ſpeaks to you by men of <hi>like-paſsions</hi> with your ſelves, unleſs you wonder at his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Mercy: For ye can neither <hi>ſee</hi> nor hear <hi>HIM</hi> and <hi>live;</hi> one glimpſe (ye know) even of <hi>CHRIST'S</hi> glorious <hi>Body,</hi> ſtruck <hi>Saul</hi> to the <hi>ground blind,</hi> and half dead: <hi>Speak Thou with us</hi> (ſaid <hi>Iſrael</hi> to <hi>Moſes</hi>) <hi>and let not GOD ſpeak with us, leſt we Die.</hi> Beſides, it is <hi>GOD'S</hi> Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative alone, to ſhew his own <hi>Strength</hi> by the moſt <hi>weak</hi> Inſtruments. It was not a man of mean Perſon and Preſence, and then a <hi>Priſoner</hi> at the Bar too, that made the ſtout <hi>Felix</hi> ſhake and <hi>tremble:</hi> It was not <hi>Elijah's</hi> word (a ſilly plain Prophet) that fell like Thunder upon the great guilty <hi>Ahab,</hi> and ſtruck a <hi>Palſie</hi> into his Joynts, and forc'd him to his <hi>Sackcloth</hi> and <hi>Aſhes;</hi> but the <hi>Word</hi> of the <hi>Living God;</hi> which if, as ſoft <hi>Fire,</hi> it cannot melt, like a ſtrong
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100574:16"/>Hammer oft breaks the Rocky Heart in pieces. The ſame <hi>GOD</hi> doth not now thunder and threaten, but <hi>pray</hi> and <hi>beſeech you by us: Hear, O Heavens, and give ear, O Earth!</hi> The Almighty <hi>Creator</hi> becomes (as it were) an humble Petitioner to his own <hi>Creature;</hi> and to ſhew he is in good earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, becauſe he could not ſwear by a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, he hath ſworn by himſelf, upon his own <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Honour, As I live (ſaith the LORD) I will not the death of a ſinner:</hi> Who can deſpiſe ſuch ardent Love? Who can ſpurn at ſuch infinite tender Bowels? Who can reſiſt that <hi>ſtill ſmall Voyce,</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, but piercing and importunate whiſpers of his Holy <hi>SPIRIT</hi> in your hearts, which the Tongue of <hi>Men and Angels</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expreſs, no, nor all the powers of <hi>Men and Devils</hi> (without your own conſent) render ineffectual? And what doth the <hi>Lord thy God</hi> thus <hi>require,</hi> nay <hi>requeſt and beſeech of thee, O Man?</hi> If he had <hi>bid thee do ſome great thing,</hi> to <hi>cure thy</hi> natural <hi>Leproſie,</hi> wouldſt thou <hi>not have done it?</hi> How much
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100574:16"/>rather then, when he ſaith unto thee, only <hi>waſh in the blood of the Covenant,</hi> and <hi>he clean?</hi> Only be <hi>reconciled,</hi> be hearty friends with thy <hi>God,</hi> make what returns thou canſt of his wonderful Love. Indeed the <hi>tinckling of three little Bells in a Country Steeple,</hi> and the Peaſants flocking to <hi>the Towns end and crying, GOD SAVE THE KING! adds not much to the Majeſty of a Potent Monarch;</hi> yet (as that great Preacher and Prelate obſerves) it <hi>is all they can do; it ſhews their honeſt love, and hearty affections, and ſo ſounds well, and pleaſes the Royal ear:</hi> Much more will your merciful God accept the will for the deed: And let but men husband their proportion of <hi>Grace</hi> as well as they can; let them but ſhew their integrity of heart, and earneſt deſires, and then do their faithful endeavours to <hi>ſerve, love</hi> and <hi>honour Him,</hi> and he asks no more; being ready to ſupply all their defects and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, out of the inexhauſtible Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of <hi>CHRISTS Righteouſneſs.</hi> This is all that <hi>God doth beſeech you by us;</hi> and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100574:17"/>if any man will deny him this, he muſt needs confeſs his <hi>Damnation is juſt;</hi> which <hi>GOD</hi> forbid, and I have done: <hi>For we are Ambaſſadors for CHRIST, as though GOD the HOLY GHOST did beſeech you by us, We pray you in CHRIST GOD THE SON'S ſtead, be ye reconciled to GOD THE FATHER.</hi> To which Eternal <hi>TRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NITY, ONE GOD,</hi> be the Eternal <hi>Kingdom, Power and Glory.</hi> AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:100574:17"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of ſome Sermons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> printed for, and ſold by <hi>Henry Brome,</hi> ſince the dreadful Fire of <hi>London,</hi> to <hi>1675.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>A Guide to Eternity, by <hi>John Bona,</hi> uſeful for Families, and fit to be given at Funerals.</item>
               <item>Dean <hi>W. Lloyd</hi>'s Sermon before the King about Miracles. 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— His Sermon at the Funeral of <hi>John</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— His Sermon before the King in Lent, 1673. 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Seaſonable Diſcourſe againſt Popery, in <hi>quarto.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— The Defence of it, <hi>quarto.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— The Difference betwixt the Church and Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> in <hi>quarto.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Papiſts Apology to the Parliament anſwered. 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Naylor</hi>'s Commemoration Sermon for the Honorable Col. <hi>Cavendiſh.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Sayers</hi> Sermon at the Aſſizes at <hi>Reading.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Tho. Tanner</hi>'s Sermon to the ſcattered Members of the Church. 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Stanhop</hi>'s four Sermons on ſeveral Occaſions, <hi>octavo</hi> bound. 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Papal Tyranny,</hi> as it was exerciſed over <hi>England</hi> for ſome Ages, with two Sermons on the fifth <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>November,</hi> by Dr. <hi>Du Moulin,</hi> in <hi>quarto.</hi> 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—His Sermon at the Funeral of Dr. <hi>Turner</hi> Dean of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury. 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Biſhop <hi>Lany</hi>'s laſt Sermon, preached before the King, againſt Comprehenſion.</item>
               <item>Principles and Duties of Natural Religion. By <hi>John Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins,</hi> late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Farindon</hi>'s 130 Sermons, in <hi>Folio.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
